- We are launching a whole new channel.
There have been video
ideas that I've pitched
that don't fully belong on "Veritasium."
- I've been in those pitch meetings.
I've seen those.
I've seen that happen.
- But that doesn't mean
that the videos shouldn't exist
and that they aren't
saying something very interesting.
We need another way to tell these stories.
- We at "Veritasium," we have a lot
of exciting stories that we want to tell.
Same Veritasium rigour,
but this time it's about social science.
It's about how our complex
and constantly changing world works.
So that's what we're doing.
We're launching a whole new
channel called "InGenius."
You can watch the first few minutes here,
and if you like it, come to our channel,
"InGenius," and you can watch the rest.
This $40 hunk of metal
rewired the modern world.
It started a revolution
that transformed China from being one
of the poorest countries in the world,
to a global superpower,
controlling 30% of all manufacturing.
It's a story that's
never been told before.
How it inspires former spy, Yuan Geng,
to create an island of capitalism
in his home county with an invention
that changes the face of communist China,
spreading its influence across the world
and upending the entire global economy.
But the story didn't start in China,
it starts with a
frustrated American trucker
from North Carolina.
(soft blues music)
In 1937,
24-year-old Malcolm McLean
is driving his truck full
of cotton bales from North Carolina
up to Hoboken, New Jersey.
At port, he waits for
his truck to be unloaded,
and waits, and waits.
It's painstakingly slow,
almost a whole day,
and that's just his one truck.
He figures, what if you took
the entire back of the truck
and just put it directly on the ship?
The whole thing would be over in a matter
of minutes instead of hours.
- So why don't we put that
whole body on the truck?
That's my first thought, you know?
- The problem is,
truck drivers can't control
how ships are loaded.
So while McLean builds a highly
successful trucking empire
over the next 20 years,
he can only stand by
and watch as the cargo issue gets worse.
This is the log from a 1954
cargo ship, the SS Warrior.
194,582 total things on the ship
that would all have to be loaded
and unloaded by hand, by
gangs of longshoremen.
It takes so long.
It means if you're shipping something,
you're paying twice as much for your cargo
to be stuck at port than
actually travelling on a ship.
And it makes your cargo
vulnerable to another problem.
The New York and New Jersey
waterfronts in the 50's
are dominated by the Genovese
and Gambino mafia families.
Corruption, racketeering
and theft are endemic.
More than $13 million
of cargo is estimated
to have been stolen just
from those ports over a three-year period.
That's more than 180
million in today's money.
The upshot is,
the process is so expensive
that in most cases selling internationally
just isn't worth it.
So most consumer products stay local,
make locally, sell locally.
So in 1955, McLane decides to act.
He's convinced his old idea
of detachable truck
trailers is the solution.
So McLean does something drastic.
He sells his 20-year-old trucking empire
and gambles everything on
an ocean shipping company,
despite the fact that he has
zero experience in the field.
But to turn his idea into
reality, he needs someone
who can actually build the
container of his dreams.
He hears about 35-year-old
engineer, Keith Tantlinger,
based out in Spokane, Washington,
who has built a transportable metal box
and even been tinkering
with trying to stack it.
Tantlinger's reasoning
is similar to McLean.
Rather than waste precious ship space
with the truck or the wheels,
just transport the cargo
in the box from the truck to
the ship in one seamless move.
McLean flies Tantlinger down
to his headquarters in Alabama
and immediately gets him
working on containers
that will fit onto a
converted World War II
oil tanker that he just bought.
McLean renames the ship the SS Ideal X,
ideal for the ideal form of transportation
and X for experimentation.
- It was the SpaceX of the 1950's
and in many ways Malcolm McLean
is the Elon Musk of his day.
(soft music)